Guide to the Oliver Martin Johnston Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Oliver Martin Johnston papers
1893-1987
1893-1947
SC0434
Johnston, Oliver Martin, 1866-
Johnston, Oliver Martin.
2.25 Linear feet
Papers primarily consist of his notebooks as a doctoral student on French and Italian grammar and literature, 1893-1895; other items include his dissertation, articles, correspondence, family history, published autobiography, and notes for sermons.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Dr. Martha Bigelow, 1991.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Oliver Martin Johnston was a professor of Romanc Languages at Stanford University from 1897 until his retirement in 1932. He received his a.b. and M.A. from Mississippi College and his Ph.D. from Johns Hopkins University in 1896. He taught one year at Bryn Mawer before joining the Stanford faculty to teach French. He served as head of the Department of Romanic Languages for twenty-two years, from 1914-1932.
Dr. Johnston was active in the First Baptish Church of Palo Alto. He was one of the founders of the Berkeley Baptist Divinity School and served on its Board of Directors for many years. prof. Johnston died in 1953.
Description of the Collection
The papers of Dr. Johnston primarily consist of his notebooks from his years as a doctoral student at John Hopkins Unviersity. The collection also includes his dissertation, articles, correspondence, greeting cards, family history, his published autobiography, notes for sermons, and other miscellaneous papers.
Access Terms
Johns Hopkins University --Students.; Johnston, Oliver Martin.; French language.; French literature.; Italian language.; Italian literature.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Correspondence. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Correpondence. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Greeting Cards, 1935-1985. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Papers and Family History. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sermon Notes and misc. Church Papers. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal Papers, Speaking Engagements. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dissertation: The Historical Syntax of the Atonic Personal Pronouns in Italian. 1898. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Autobiography: The Measure of a Man. 1947. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Notebook: Italian Literature (1894), Physiological Phonetics (1894). (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Italian (1895, Paris Research Notes). (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notebook: Italian (1894-1895). (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notebook: Italian Texts (1895, Johns Hopkins). (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notebook: Italian Literature (1895, Johns Hopkins). (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notebook: Italian-English Notebook. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Notebook: Italian. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notebook: Italian Grammar. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Notebook: Italian. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Notebook: Italian (1894-95)., 1894-1895 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Notebook: Italian Grammar. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notebook: Italian Grammar. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 2 Notebooks: Italian. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Notebook: Italian Grammar. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Notebook: Italian Grammar. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Notebook: Italian (1895, Milan). (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Notebook:Old French Phonology (1893), Modern French Literature (1895). Johns Hopkins University. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Notebook: Old French Phonology (1893). (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Notebook: Fables of Marie de France (1894). (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notebook: The New Moral Drift in French Literature (1894); Spanish Literature (1894). (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Notebook: Lectures on Old French Literature by F.M. Warren (1896, John Hopkins University). (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Notebook: Misc. French, Greek, English (1894-95)., 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Notebook: French grammar (n.d.). (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Notebook: Literature (1894, Paris). (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Notebook: Old French Literature; Modern French Literature (1896). (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Notebook: Paleography (n.d.). (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Notebook: History (1894). (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Notebook: Literature; Composition (n.d.). (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Notebook: Medieval Versions of Ant and Grasshopper. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Notebook: Mind and Scope of Negro Education; Elementary French; Modern French (n.d.). (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Notebook: French grammatical history (n.d.). (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Notebook: Biblioteque Nationa1e research notes (Paris, 1895). (Box 5, Folder 4)